# **Andy Gross**

1800 Bryant Street Apt. 305 – San Francisco, CA 94110 + 1 (415) 335 6775 • andy@andygross.org • <math> andy@andygross.org argv0 Conference Presentations: http://lanyrd.com/profile/argv0

## Summary

I'm a recognized expert on distributed systems, databases, and cloud architectures with over 15 years of experience building world class products, services, and engineering teams. I am the primary author of Riak, an influential and commercially successful NoSQL database. I'm seeking technology/product leadership and founder opportunities at venture funded startups.

## **Experience**

Opsee San Francisco, CA

Co-founder and CTO

2/2015-7/2015

A developer-oriented monitoring company founded with friends. I brought investors into our 1.5 MM seed round, hired the initial engineering team, and led implementation of the MVP product.

Twitter San Francisco, CA

Staff Software Engineer, Core Storage

3/2014-2/2015

I was a technical lead for Manhattan, Twitter's self-serve internal DBaaS, and other projects in the Core Storage group.

- Implemented a distributed rate limiting and admission control system based on control theory to prevent cluster overload.
- Authored an integration testing tool to automate verification of cluster inv ariants and correctness checking.
- o Wrote a dynamic configuration framework for Manhattan, allowing system configuration to be changed at runtime.

Basho Technologies San Francisco, CA

Chief Architect, VP of Engineering

12/2007-3/2014

I authored Riak, Basho's flagship product. I defined the technical and product direction as we grew the company from four to 140 employees in San Francisco, Cambridge, Herndon, London, and Tokyo.

- o Authored initial versions of all Basho Open Source and Enterprise software (Riak, RiakCS, Riak Enterprise Replication).
- o Built engineering team, participated in fundraising, closed deals with Fortune 50 companies (Apple, Comcast, AT&T, Verizon, State Farm).
- o Presented at conferences on distributed systems, lectured at Berkeley and Stanford on distributed systems in industry.

Mochi Media San Francisco, CA

Senior Systems Architect

5/2007-12/2007

I was hired as employee #3. I helped secure funding from Accel and rewrote MVP infrastructure (messaging, monitoring, DevOps tools) to handle post-launch growth. I left to start Basho with Akamai colleagues.

Apple Cupertino, CA

Distributed Systems Engineer, Developer Tools

9/2005-5/2007

I was recruited onto the Xcode team to write a distributed compiler to speed up build time for Apple's largest third party developers (Adobe, Microsoft).

- o Designed and implemented a distributed filesystem (see Patents and Publications).
- o Maintenance and feature development for the Xcode build system.
- o Presented work at WWDC 2006.

Akamai Technologies Cambridge, MA

Senior Software Engineer, Government and Custom Engineering, Systems Engineering

7/1999-9/2005

Employee #75. I was hired to carry 21" CRT monitors for new hires, and left as a Senior Engineer leading design and development of custom high-margin products for the US Government.

- o Implemented a reactive overlay network for a government customer that became the basis for Akamai's highly profitable IP acceleration products.
- o Created an analytics application aggregating IDS, BGP, and performance data for the US Intelligence Community.
- o Developed Akamai Content Storage, the distributed storage system backing the initial Apple iTunes Music Store launch.

### **Patents and Publications**

Bumgarner, William, Adam Swift, and Andrew Gross (2012). "MIRRORED FILE SYSTEM". US8286127 B2. Gross, Andrew R. (2012). "The Architecture of Open Source Applications". In: vol. i. Chap. Riak and Erlang.

#### Education

University of ConnecticutStorrs, CTManagement, Finance,1996–1999

Left to take pre-IPO position at Akamai